welcome to meditating with john vervicky
i am a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the university of
toronto
i academically teach and scientifically
study mindfulness
and related phenomena like insight flow
mystical experience transformative
experience higher states of
consciousness
the cultivation of wisdom and the
aspiration towards enlightenment
i've been practicing the past meditation
meta contemplation tai chi chuan
chi kung for over 29 years and teaching
them
professionally for close to 20 years if
you're joining for the first time
welcome
but please know that this is a
progressive course the introductory
course
is done and we are now moving on to
advanced techniques that are taught
every second monday
which is our dharma day if you want to
catch up
please check the links in the
description of this video where you'll
find links to previous lessons
you'll be able to catch up and keep
going with us
tuesdays through fridays we sit together
at the end of every day
monday through friday there's q a please
keep the q
a um these q a to the ecology of
practices that are being taught in this
course
if you have more encompassing questions
you want to ask
please come to the monthly q a that's
live stream on youtube
every third friday of the month i
believe that's
june 19th coming up at 3 p.m eastern
time
so we've done the review of lectio
davina and i've done also another uh
example of it for you uh and we have to
do a
pretty uh tight uh closing today uh so
let's move towards getting to the
practice if i could ask you a few things
uh please remember to like this video to
raise its visibility
on youtube uh please make sure that
you have you know your posture set
you've set your phones on do not disturb
and
we will begin when i say begin
be good
you
so
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you cultivated in your
practice
with your everyday consciousness and
cognition perhaps by reciting the five
promises to yourself
so uh let's ask uh some and sorry let's
answer some questions
i have a question from karima can you
recommend a translator for the
upanishads
um i have a translation i can't remember
the name of it right now
i'll try to remember it for uh tomorrow
and i'll show you the translation that i
found
quite good quite good
uh there's a question from lysol van
wick
how do we deal with guard against
self-deception during
inquiring mindfulness and lectio
so this this is a question
that um
i wanna i wanna convey the my attitude
towards us accurately
this this is not something i'm
complaining this is something that i'm
noting because it's important it's a
question we keep coming back to
many people ask it again and again and
again
and i want to i want to pause and
valorize how important this question is
this idea of bringing the whole issue
of self-deception into the heart
of our practices now what we
and i think so this is deeply important
and so what we have to do then is
respond
to the centrality of this in a
comprehensive manner if we
are looking for some introspective mark
you know chances are we're not going to
you know won't possess it
we're not going to be able to find it
instead what you have to do is you have
to start in comprehensive practice of
trying to note self-deception in your
life
so one of the things i do is historic
practice of journaling
at the end of every day i learn about
all the cognitive biases
all the ways in which involve prayer to
self-deception so the cognitive biases
and then the machinery you know that
makes us be self-centered
self-important self-righteous learn much
as much as
i can about that in psychology and then
i try to note it throughout the day
and then i journal about it both the
positive and the negative
when you know when i caught it or uh the
you know the evidence that i probably
didn't catch it but it was effective in
my
affecting things in my life and so you
have to do this very reliably you have
to practice
looking for self-deception it's a skill
and a sensitivity and a sense of self
therefore a virtue
it has to be actively cultivated
independently
of whichever specific instance you want
to apply it
because it's precisely when you're in
the midst
of the processing that it's most
difficult to cultivate
the virtue of seeing through illusion
the core of wisdom
as you apply that skill
first take note if as you're doing this
is
are they are they taking your life
right two senses do you feel like
they're starting
to present you're starting
the patterns that you are realizing this
practice
are they starting to affect ability to
solve
problems to step back from
self-centeredness
to notice more the self the instances of
self
uh deception that you're training to
be more honest with yourself and others
to be more honorable to others
and to yourself are you noticing all of
this and as you notice this does it take
for you
in other words in the sense of those
patterns you now start to spontaneously
see those patterns
emerging within your practice and it's
that loop that loop of reciprocal
opening
in which the independently trained skill
virtue
of seeing through illusion is reliably
and systematically and systemically
presencing itself
when that's forming then you have
good reason especially like so
you start to be able to make sense of
things and when you read other people
who are on the path
oh i get this more i understand what
they're talking about
like all of that and especially if
other people notice this for
these virtues in you in your life
that's how you can tell when you're
on the right path when that you're
reliably because you can never do it
perfectly
but you're reliably challenging
self-deception that last point is
crucial
if you set yourself the standard the
cartesian standard of i want perfection
i want certainty then you
you you it's like trying to find the
perfect posture in your sitting
you cannot find it because you have the
capacity to doubt
anything that you bring to bear in order
to alleviate your doubt
so at some point you have to engage i'm
not accusing
you listen particularly i'm speaking to
all of us myself included
you have to engage in the sense of do i
have a reliable
sense that other people are mirroring
back to me a diversity of responsible
and honorable people
all right right mirroring back to me do
i have a reliable sense of continuity of
contact
with a reciprocal opening between my
practice
and my life
that's all we have time for today but
that was a really important question
and i'm happy to come back to that
question again
and again and again we all have to learn
there is a virtue to doubting so
aristotle's idea is every virtue is
between a deficit
and an excess you can not doubt enough
or you can doubt too much but doubting
for the right reason to the right degree
at the right time
for the right purpose that's the virtue
you're trying to cultivate
so thank you all for joining and as
always thank you to my dear friend and
techno major maher my beloved son jason
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video
on my channel you'll find a lecture
series awakening from the meeting crisis
in a discussion series uh voices with
raviki
where all of these topics are developed
in depth in situated with a more
encompassing
uh ecology of practices way of life
orientation towards being
please invite others who might benefit
to share this video help
as many people as i can i'm doing this
to try and be as helpful
as i can dude
excellent player gout that is often here
on the chat part of the senate there is
a
group of people who meet on the discord
server do the practice get a discussion
there's excellent
they've had some i've i've heard they've
had some excellent uh discussions with
people from voices of the
vicky paul vander clay gregon reeks and
people talking about all of this
this is a vibrant vibrant and vital
community
you want to check out the link to the
discord server
will be in the notes description for
this video
remember we're doing this every weekday
morning at 9 30
eastern time remember
continuity of practice remember what i
was just talking about in fact
continuity of practice more important
than quantity
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind and body
there is no friend no true ally
greater than your mind and body
be lamps unto yourself take care
everyone
i'll see you tomorrow
you